<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="en">
	<title>Brian&#39;s Blog</title>
	<subtitle>Thoughts on ideas concerning the church, society, and technology</subtitle>
	<link href="https://brianroberg.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://brianroberg.com/"/>
	<updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
	<id>https://brianroberg.com</id>
	<author>
		<name>Brian Roberg</name>
		<email>brian@brianroberg.com</email>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Book Review: Essentialism by Greg McKeown</title>
		<link href="https://brianroberg.com/blog/essentialism/"/>
		<updated>2022-03-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://brianroberg.com/blog/essentialism/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is possible to read Greg McKeown’s 2014 book &lt;em&gt;Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less&lt;/em&gt; as a collection of techniques for time management. There is some promise to this approach, as McKeown has gathered together a number of astute observations and suggestions to help readers better manage their priorities. But overall I believe that anyone who truly wants to improve their productivity would do better to skip this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I describe where I see this book falling short, I&#39;ll give it credit for its strengths. There are some good reasons that people I respect have found this book valuable enough to make it required reading in DiscipleMakers’ staff training program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principal strength of the book is that it unflinchingly presents the inescapability of trade-offs in decision-making. As Oliver Burkeman described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://brianroberg.micro.blog/2022/01/31/book-review-four.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; there is a tendency among productivity gurus to promise that, if only you master their technique, you will be able to achieve all your life’s ambitions without having to say “no” to any deeply-held desires. McKeown rejects this false promise, early and often. In fact, the characteristic flaw of McKeown’s “Non-Essentialist” bogeyman is his inability (or unwillingness) to admit that we can only say “yes” to one thing by saying “no” to many other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If realism about trade-offs is the main strength of the book, it also does a good job presenting various corollary arguments. For example, McKeown convincingly describes the dangers of over-optimistic planning and makes a good case for the importance of including buffer in our schedules. He provides a useful survey of research into cognitive biases that affect our decision-making. Also, his discussion of the value of routine and habit confirmed my inclination to read further on this topic. While there were points when his manner of presentation verges on the trivial, the book undoubtedly has some solid content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, my overall evaluation of the book is not positive. In fact, I feel I can&#39;t write about this book  without describing the magnitude of my subjective reaction to it. I found myself viscerally disliking the book to a degree I rarely experience. While many complaints come to mind, I will focus my critique to two points: one concerning style, the other a matter of more substance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stylistically, I found McKeown&#39;s approach to his topic to be off-puttingly pretentious. As I&#39;ve said, the book contains some solid content relating to time management and prioritization. But McKeown talks a much bigger game than that. He wants you to believe that Essentialism(TM) will transform your life and unlock a life of true fulfillment. He says this explicitly in his concluding chapter, but he works to build an aura of grandeur throughout the book. He often does this by associating his ideas with the lives of revered people, including Rosa Parks and Mohandas Gandhi. Or he draws (superficial) connections to the ideas of noted  thinkers. At one point he name-drops Aristotle and Heidegger in the same paragraph. But I found all this unconvincing. The overall impression is that of a business school student wearing a philosophy department sweatshirt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my biggest objection with &lt;em&gt;Essentialism&lt;/em&gt; is not its pretentious lack of substance. The substance it does have is even more troubling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding his puffed-up presentation, McKeown does make claims about what it means to live a virtuous life. The problem is that his system of ethics is thoroughly unbiblical. The highest ethical imperative for the Essentialist is not to love God or to love other people; it is to realize one&#39;s own ambitions. The Essentialist must steadfastly reject opportunities that do not advance his own interests, period. Self-sacrificial service is moral failure. And he doesn&#39;t merely imply this. He states it explicitly, and even strengthens his case by invoking respected figures like Peter Drucker who make the same claim. The instances in which he praises people for choosing to spend time with loved ones are not counter-examples, because in these cases the Essentialist has decided that investing in those relationships is what self-actualization looks like (for now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is why I believe that the technical merits of &lt;em&gt;Essentialism&lt;/em&gt; do not make up for its faults: McKeown&#39;s  productivity advice and his self-centered framework are inextricably linked. While some chapters contain more self-advancement than others, this ethic is the foundation of the book. It&#39;s what gives McKeown leverage in his exhortations that we slim down our commitments. It&#39;s what allows him to propose heuristics like his &amp;quot;90% Rule&amp;quot; without getting bogged down in questions of justice for the people affected by our decisions (such as job applicants). It&#39;s how he can talk up the value of setting boundaries in relationships without troubling himself to distinguish the difference between enabling and helping. In sum, whenever the interests of another person start to impinge on a would-be Essentialist&#39;s personal agenda, he offers a license to write that person off like a bad debt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These considerations lead me to conclude that whatever assets the book may have, its liabilities far outweigh them. As I noted at the beginning, it comes closest if your aim is simply to gain some insight into techniques for time management. But if this is your goal, I suggest you would do better to go right to the source and read the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/em&gt; articles that represent the wisdom of the business school world. If you want to go deeper with a book that explores the intersection of technique and biblical motivation, I&#39;d suggest Matt Perman&#39;s &lt;em&gt;What&#39;s Best Next&lt;/em&gt;. While it&#39;s been quite a while since I read that book,  I&#39;m considering picking it up again. I suspect I may find even more value in it now by contrast with &lt;em&gt;Essentialism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Book Review: Four Thousand Weeks by Oliver Burkeman</title>
		<link href="https://brianroberg.com/blog/four-thousand-weeks/"/>
		<updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://brianroberg.com/blog/four-thousand-weeks/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every once in a while I&#39;ve looked for a book that presents a cogent and intellectually honest case for finding meaning in life, but without reference to God. My various casual searches were thwarted by the fact that the most prominent books that are tagged as “atheist” tend towards polemic. Since most real people are not polemicists, I judged such books unhelpful for understanding the views of people I might actually talk to. I’d given up looking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of this desire as I read Oliver Burkeman&#39;s new book, &lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals&lt;/em&gt;. As indicated by its subtitle, the nominal topic of the book is time management.  But the real scope of the book is both broader and deeper. In fact, I think a more accurate (if less marketable) subtitle would be something like &lt;em&gt;An Atheist’s Guide to Living Well.&lt;/em&gt; In the end I concluded that this book delivers not only helpful insights related to time management, but also a broader perspective toward life that I found valuable to read even though I profoundly disagree with some of Burkeman’s basic premises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burkeman takes it as a given that there is no God—at least no God about whom we can know enough that He should figure into any of our decision-making. But Burkeman’s tone is nothing like that of the strident atheists who sell books by railing against God. In fact, both times he quotes Scripture in the book he does so with a respectful tone (even if one of the quotes was taken out of context). But it was a verse of Scripture he did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; quote which best captures a major part of Burkeman’s thesis. That verse is James 4:14: “Yet you do not know what tomorrow will bring. What is your life? For you are a mist that appears for a little time and then vanishes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principal virtue of this book is that it provides—in effect, if not by intent—a clear, thorough, and insightful exploration of the implications of James 4:14. The “four thousand weeks” of the title refers to the number of weeks (roughly) in an 80-year life span, and Burkeman does an excellent job calling out ways in which we tend to ignore the fact of our mortality—especially in the peculiar corner of the self-help publishing world that focuses on time management and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burkeman asserts that time management is a failed discipline, and not only because it doesn’t deliver on its promises in terms of objective productivity. The more fundamental problem with time management technique is the implicit promise that usually lies &lt;em&gt;behind&lt;/em&gt; the technique: that if you just master the technique, you will achieve mastery over your life as well as freedom from the nagging feeling that your life is slipping through your fingers. Burkeman counters this seductive promise with hard reality. We are going to die. We are &lt;em&gt;finite beings&lt;/em&gt; who are inescapably bound to limitations in time and opportunity. To the degree that time management promises that we can accomplish everything that’s important to us so that we’ll never have to say “no” to opportunities we’d really like to pursue—to that degree, time management is a delusion that disconnects us from reality and diminishes our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burkeman is relentless in driving this home in one area of life after another. I lost track of how many times he said some variation of “This might sound bleak, but there’s freedom in acknowledging that it’s true.” I actually found this quite refreshing, as it reflects a pattern of argumentation that acknowledges that what we believe about ourselves doesn’t matter if our beliefs don’t conform to the true nature of reality. It also reflected his priorities in what he wanted to convey. He was clearly more interested in helping readers think clearly in the big picture than he was in teaching particular techniques. For example, whereas he mentioned David Allen once, he devoted several pages to discussing Martin Heidegger’s philosophy about man in relation to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that the book was entirely ethereal. For instance, Burkeman suggested a litmus test for judging a particular time management technique: whether the technique helps you “neglect the right things.” Techniques are helpful insofar as they help surface the hard decisions about which opportunities to pursue and which to reject. On the other hand, he said, be wary of techniques that obscure or defer such decisions, and especially of those that deny that such decisions are necessary. (Though Burkeman did not call out many techniques by name, he did single out the “Big Rocks” illustration from Stephen Covey&#39;s book &lt;em&gt;First Things First&lt;/em&gt;, calling it a “lie.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burkeman is similarly incisive in handling topics such as procrastination, attention, distraction, and rest. In each of these areas he went deeper than I had thought before and made connections I hadn’t made before. His discussion on these topics is worth the time of reading the book on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as I mentioned earlier, the book is not so much &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; time management as that it uses time management as a rendezvous point for an expedition into the question of how to live life well. I will still commend Burkeman as a worthy guide in this endeavor, but with an important qualification. Christians who have a solid biblical understanding of who they are in relation to God and the world can benefit from Burkeman’s secular take on how to find meaning in life. People without a biblical grounding, however, could be led astray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, if James 4:14 helps us see the virtues of this book, the following verse—James 4:15—serves as an indictment of its shortcomings. That verse says, “Instead you ought to say, ‘If the Lord wills, we will live and do this or that.’” Burkeman does not believe that God’s will should figure into our decision-making, so his guidance concerning the ultimate ground of our decision-making leads him to unbiblical conclusions. Like the Preacher of Ecclesiastes, he provides valuable insight regarding matters under the sun but has little to say about eternal matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I do want to credit Burkeman for his intellectual honesty. A less careful non-theist might assert that human life has inherent dignity and meaning, forgetting that for life to be &lt;em&gt;inherently&lt;/em&gt; meaningful it must receive that meaning from something outside itself. (In the Christian conception, every person has dignity and purpose because every person is created in the image of God.) Burkeman, in contrast, shoulders the harder work of carving out a path for a person to imbue his own life with meaning in the midst of an indifferent universe. (He does this along existentialist lines, investing tremendous weight in the sanctity of human self-determination.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, I would recommend &lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/em&gt; to anyone looking to better understand the constraints we face as limited creatures. It is a rare book that earnestly seeks meaning in life while taking care not to smuggle in ideas that derive from some form of theism. Within these constraints (i.e. under the sun) it offers wisdom. In addition, its vivid picture of the struggle to construct meaning for one’s own life could also help Christians as they share with their secular friends how the gospel expands the horizon of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
